<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Relief of apprentices wronged by their masters how by our law it may effectually be given and obtain'd, without any special new act of Parliament for that purpose.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11926348</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11926348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51034</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61441)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51034)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Relief of apprentices wronged by their masters how by our law it may effectually be given and obtain'd, without any special new act of Parliament for that purpose.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Clark...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus).  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apprentices --  England --  London.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51034:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51034:1"/>
            <p>RELIEF OF APPRENTICES Wronged by their MASTERS.</p>
            <p>HOW By our <hi>Law</hi> it may effectually be given and obtain'd, without any ſpecial New <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>With Allowance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Clark,</hi> near St. <hi>Pauls-Wharf,</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51034:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51034:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Jeffries,</hi> Baron of <hi>Wem,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> and one of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council, Sir <hi>Robert Wright,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> And the reſt of the Honourable Judges.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhips,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE encloſed Paper is deſigned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the True, but Latent Cauſes and Occaſions of a great Abuſe very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and notorious in this City of <hi>London,</hi> and of very pernicious conſequence throughout the whole Kingdom; to ſhew the Iniquity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of certain falſe Principles and Opinions which ſupport it; and for a check to the Abuſe and Encouragement to ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:51034:3"/>need Relief to, ſhew how by our Laws effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Remedy may be given without any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial New Act of Parliament. For the Abuſe is ſuch, and ſo common and notorious, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Parliament-men have thought it worthy of a ſpecial Act of Parliament to reſtrain it. But if effectual Remedy may be had without it, it is preſum'd, that that will be more Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for our Laws, and therefore that the tender of it to the conſideration of your Lordſhips will be no ungrateful Service. It is alſo hoped, that the Approbation of it by your Lordſhips Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, will not only give Life to the Remedy herein mentioned, but even of it ſelf, give great Check to ſuch Abuſes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51034:3"/>
            <head>RELIEF OF APPRENTICES Wronged by their MASTERS. HOW By our <hi>Law</hi> it may effectually be given and obtain'd, without any ſpecial new <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament for that purpoſe.</head>
            <p>IT is certain, and generally known to moſt men acquainted with the Occurrences in this City of <hi>London,</hi> that of thoſe Youths who are daily put Apprentices here, a very great number do miſcarry, and never come to exerciſe the Trades to which they were put: And of thoſe, though many miſcarry through their own fault, yet that very many do miſcarry either through the Careleſneſs and Negligence, or the Harſhneſs and unreaſonable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, or (which too often happens) through the ill Deſigns and Practices of their Maſters.</p>
            <p>This is ſo common and notorious, that there is no part of the Nation which hath not many examples of ſuch unhappy young men, who might have been very uſeful in their Generation, but by theſe means are driven either into ill Courſes, or become altogether
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51034:4"/>uſeleſs to the Publick, and a burden to their Relations.</p>
            <p>And therefore, ſince the beſt and wiſeſt even of Heathen States have been uſually very provident for the Education of their Youth, it might be thought a very great defect in us if we ſhould be deſtitute of ſufficient Remedy, for ſo notorious an Abuſe, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great moment.</p>
            <p>But I'm of opinion, that, if the matter be well conſider'd, neither are our Legiſlators, nor our Laws already conſtituted, to be blam'd in this reſpect. Not <hi>our Legiſlators;</hi> For Abuſes will, like evil Weeds, be alwaies growing up even in the beſt conſtituted States: And it will be ſome time e'er they be obſerved; And it will again, after they are obſerv'd, require ſome time to find out and ſettle a proper Remedy for them. And for thoſe Abuſes whereof I ſpeak, they have not, certainly, been of any long time practis'd, or however not ſo notoriouſly and commonly, but have by degrees grown more frequent and notorious, as the Rates which men have given with Apprentices, have been raiſed; which are now (within theſe twenty years laſt paſt, or little more) riſen to that height, that may well prove a Temptation to men who are continually employ'd in Buſineſs for Gain, and are not punctually and reſolutely Honeſt. And therefore, it is no wonder if now, more than heretofore, in ſo great a City, there be many men noted to have had many Apprentices, but never any that came to any thing in their Trade; and are reaſonably enough ſuſpected to make a kind of Trade of it, to take great Summs of Money with Apprentices, and in a year or two, or ſome ſhort time, upon ſome pretence or other, to turn them off with little, and take others again with great Summs in their places: and that divers ill arts and practices have been obſerv'd to have been us'd by ſuch perſons to bring their Deſigns about, and worſe to put ſome colour upon their dealings when they have been queſtion'd for the ſame: For Credit and Reputation is of ſo great importance to a Trader, that he who makes light of the Ruin of a man, is not likely to make ſcruple of the uſe of any means, though never ſo vile and wicked, to ſave that which is of ſo great concern to him.</p>
            <p>But theſe things, I am inform'd, have been ſome years ſince obſerv'd and taken into conſideration, in order to the providing of a Remedy, by divers worthy Members of Parliament, though nothing yet, by reaſon of various occurrences intervening, hath been offer'd to the Houſe. But that which I am inform'd, was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51034:4"/>thought by ſome the moſt effectual Remedy, was by a ſhort Act of Parliament, to make all Bonds void which ſhould be given for the Fidelity of Apprentices.</p>
            <p>This I confeſs, might ſeem an effectual means to make the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter more careful of them. And it is an Argument, that thoſe Gentlemen were very ſenſible of the notoriouſneſs of the Abuſe, who could think ſo ſevere a Remedy neceſſary. But I cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it: For, 1. I think it not ſo effectual a means for the end intended, as is preſumed: For a Maſter who had a Deſign upon his Apprentice, might notwithſtanding leave him liberty enough to do thoſe things, from which he might take a pretence to turn him off and diſappoint him of his Trade, and yet be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Gainer out of the Money he had received. 2. it is a reſtraint of a reaſonable and neceſſary Security; and though it might be reaſonable, could it be applied only to ill Men; yet foraſmuch as it would be equally inconvenient and grievous to the moſt innocent and honeſt Maſters, as to the worſt of all, I think it unreaſonable. 3. It would be apt to put honeſt and good Men upon almoſt the like Rigor and Severity, for their own Security, which is ſuppoſed to be practiced by ill Men for their Advantage. 4. It ſeems to me to be attended with no leſs Inconvenience to the Publick, than that which is deſigned to be remedied by it: For the Conſequence would be, that, neither would Maſters know how to take Apprentices; nor would others be able to get Places and Employments for their Children, without great difficulty and trouble.</p>
            <p>And beſides all this, I think it needleſs: For I am of opinion, (with ſubmiſſion to better Judgments) that in this, as in divers other Caſes, <hi>our Laws</hi> are not ſo defective, as ſome Men other wiſe of Wit and Parts enough, but not ſufficiently acquainted with them, do imagine; and that there is no great need to encreaſe the bulk of our Statues, (which is grown very large already) by a new Law for this Purpoſe. For I take it that our Courts of Juſtice have power and Authority already ſufficient, (and we ought not to ſuſpect them to be unwilling to uſe it upon ſo juſt and neceſſary occaſion) to give Remedy in this caſe, if the <hi>Occaſions and Encouragements</hi> to ſuch Abuſes be well conſidered. And the principal Encouragements, I take to be from the great Diſcouragements Men commonly meet with, in ſeeking Relief: And theſe again, if we trace them to their Seat, will be found to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51034:5"/>proceed partly from certain falſe and <hi>miſtaken Principles or Opinions,</hi> which like many Cuſtoms, have inſenſibly crept in, and are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally received among the Citizens; whereby Men, whoſe honeſty and ſincerity otherwiſe I do not in the leaſt queſtion, are ordinarily impoſed upon and miſled in their Judgments and Verdicts; and partly from the great Diſadvantage many Men are under for the proſecuting of any Suit in ſuch caſe, by reaſon of the diſtance of their Habitations from this City.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Of theſe miſtaken Principles, one is, <hi>That the Maſter for an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Fault in his Apprentice, eſpecially if he be found to have wronged him in his Money or Goods, though but to the value of twenty Shillings, or ſome ſuch ſmall ſumm, may turn him away, and that there is no remedy.</hi> This I know to be a common received Opinion, even with underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and very honeſt and worthy Citizens, and ſuch as do neither, practice it themſelves, nor approve it in others. Yet they think if a Man will be ſo ſevere and mercileſs as to ruine a young-man for ſuch a matter, he may do it without remedy.</p>
            <p>It is certainly contrary to Natural Equity and Juſtice, not only to the Laws of Chriſtianity, but even of Humanity. For the conſequence thereof to the Young-man, is rarely leſs than his Ruine, at leaſt the loſs of his Trade; and that ſuch perhaps (as it often happens) for which he might have had thoſe Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which he could not have for any other: But uſually it is a diſappointment of all: For having ſerved in one Trade till he be too old to be put to another, and being turn'd away by his Maſter, it is rare that another of the ſame Trade eſpecially will take him, ſo that he becomes thereby diſappointed of all. Now ſhould we look upon this under the Notion of <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> it is very Unreaſonable, for Puniſhments ought to bear ſome proportion to the Fault, eſpecially ſuch as are not Publick. But here is no proportion between them. Beſides the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Perſon ought, to be conſidered: They are not men of Age and Experience in the World, but young raw Youths, who are put Apprentices. There ought alſo to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the ſpecial Obligations upon the Maſter, which aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the matter, of which more preſently. Or ſhould we look upon it as neceſſary for the Maſters <hi>Security;</hi> that indeed might ſeem reaſonable, had the maſter no Security. But when the maſter hath a ſpecial Security to Indemnifie him, that cannot be neceſſary, nor excuſable: And the very demand and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51034:5"/>by the maſter of that Security, is an Evidence, that upon that Security, he ought to continue to train up his Apprentice in his Trade. And to come to thoſe ſpecial Obligations of the Maſter. 1. In the very agreement there is a tacit Truſt and Confidence of kindneſs to and care of the Apprentice repoſed in the Maſter by the Parent or Relations; and undertaken by the Maſter in conſideration of a good ſum of money, ſo that the Maſter doth in many reſpects ſucceed in the Place and care of the Parent or Relation who placed the Apprentice with him, whereby he is under a ſpecial Obligation to them. 2. And with the Apprentice he enters into expreſs Covenants by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, and thoſe not Conditional, but Abſolute, ſo that a Breach by one Party, doth not diſſolve the Obligation of the other, not in Natural Juſtice, no more than it doth by our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Laws, as is well known to ſuch as underſtand them, that it doth not, but only obligeth to a proportional Satisfaction. And though this doth abundantly ſhew the iniquity of it, yet we may further add, that there is no Conſiderate man, but if he percieve in the Maſter ſo great a Prejudice againſt the Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice whom he placed with him, that he would otherwiſe Turn him away, or did but ſuſpect he would not ſhew him that Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Juſtice in reſpect of his Trade which he ought to do, would of his own accord ſeek out for another Place for him, and then upon any reaſonable terms come to a fair concluſion with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſter to take him away. Therefore when notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this, the Maſter who hath good Security to Indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ll proceed to that Severity, it is <hi>A ſtrong preſumption of ſome ill deſign</hi> in him, either to get the money, or a good part thereof, or to diſappoint the Apprentice of his future Trade, leſt it ſhould prove a detriment to his own. And for the moſt part in ſuch Caſes, other circumſtances in the manner of doing it occur, from which an obſervant man may ſatisfie himſelf, though he may not have Proof enough of the circumſtances to ſatisfie a Jury.</p>
            <p>And now, ſhould we examine this by the excellent Laws of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, which doth ſo highly confirm, improve and enforce all the Laws of natural Juſtice and Equity; that plain law of Juſtice, <hi>Doing as we would be done to,</hi> that great Law of Charity to all men, and that generous Law of Indulgence and remitting Injuries, and <hi>Doing good even to Enemies;</hi> what can we really judge of ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51034:6"/>Men, but that they who can ſo eaſily caſt off the very Laws of natural Juſtice and Humanity, cannot poſſibly retain any thing of Chriſtianity in reality, but only an external profeſſion thereof in compliance and conformity to the Modes and Cuſtoms of their Countrey?</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Another</hi> of theſe miſtaken Principles is, <hi>That upon an Action brought for ſuch a cauſe, greater Damages are not to be recovered than the Money paid with the Apprentice.</hi> And this alſo I know to be a common received Opinion, and even with very Honeſt and Worthy Citizens. I have known them who have been ſo far from acting upon theſe Principles, that being wronged in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable matters by Apprentices, have not only been contented with a moderate Satisfaction for the Wrong, but moreover have become Interceſſors for them with their provoked, angry and ſevere Parents, and in meer Commiſeration for the Youths, who muſt otherwiſe have been Undone, retained them in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; (Which Moderation and Charity hath been well requited by the Fidelity and Induſtry of the ſame Apprentices afterwards) yet were ſtrongely poſſeſſed with theſe Opinions, not as reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in themſelves, but as what had ſo far prevailed in the City, that they thought it in vain for any Man to expect better, or to attempt it. And of all I have diſcourſed with, I have not yet met with one Citizen of another Opinion. And that this alſo is as inconſiſtent with natural Juſtice and Equity, as it is with our Laws, may appear by what hath been ſaid already: For as Puniſhments ought to bear proportion to the Fault, ſo ought Reparations to the Wrong. The Wrong done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this caſe is the diſappointment of a man of his Trade and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>re Lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. And for the Reparation, it is to be conſidered, that ſhould the Maſter retain the money, that would ſo much the more encreaſe the Wrong, and therefore if he reſtore the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he doth thereby only forbear a further Wrong, but makes no Reparation for that of which I ſpake. Beſides there is no juſt proportion between the Money given with the Apprentice and the Trade. And therefore did the Maſter inſtead of reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what he had received, give as much of his own, it might not be an equal Recompence for the Wrong, which may be greater than five or ten times ſo much. The very diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Trade might be ſuch: But there might beſides be ſome eſpecial Circumſtances in it very conſiderable; on the part
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51034:6"/>of the Apprentice, ſome eſpecial Advantages for that Trade, for that is a thing which men in choice of Trades for Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices have often a reſpect to: On the Maſters part an ill deſign to diſappoint him of it. For it hath been a known Practice of ill Maſters when they have found that their Apprentices if they ſhould ſet up, were likely to carry away or intercept ſome part of that Trade, which they already had or expected, to uſe divers Stratagems and Policies to diſappoint them thereof. And the greater the Advantages the Apprentice might have for his Trade, the greater the temptation to the Maſter to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him of it. And though a young Lad through inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and imprudence by a ſmall Fault, might give his Maſter an advantage againſt him, yet it might be but what the Maſter did ly at Catch for to compaſs what he deſign'd. And in ſuch caſes, beſides the private Wrong to the Apprentice, ought alſo to be taken into Conſideration, the publick miſchief of Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to ſuch Abuſes, by ill Example and Impunity.</p>
            <p n="3">III. And yet there is <hi>Another</hi> of theſe falſe Principles, which goes further, and yet is generally received; which I ſhould think very Strange and Incredible, did I not find it ſo, and conſider the great power and prevalance of Opinions taken up and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced without due Examination, and how common it is for men to do ſo. For they think it very reaſonable out of the money received, and to be reſtored, to make an <hi>Allowance for Lodging and Diet.</hi> But how unreaſonable this is, to repeat nothing of what hath been ſaid before, may appear upon theſe further Conſiderations: Firſt, the Maſter hath the uſe and benefit of the money all the while, which in many Trades, where the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is uſually the beſt, is very conſiderable, 80 or 100 <hi>l.</hi> and in ſome 200, 300, 400 and 500 <hi>l.</hi> (for to ſuch Rates are ſome now come.) And though money may be had for Six <hi>per cent</hi> and under, upon good Security, yet Trades-men could not do as they do, if they did not make at leaſt 20 <hi>per cent</hi> in the way of Trade, or by frequent returns in the Year; and to take it up at Intereſt, is not for their Credit, which is a tender thing and of great Concernment to a Trader. Again the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apprentice for the firſt Years is uſually but of little Advantage to himſelf; and if it were more, is all loſt by his diſappointment of his Trade; but from firſt to laſt of conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable uſe and benefit, and every day more and more to the Maſter.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51034:7"/>There are few Underſtanding Trades-men but know how to employ one fit to be put Apprentice in ſuch things as would coſt them more than the Maintainance of their Apprentice to hire another to do. An ordinary Servant hath uſually his Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance and good Wages beſides, for leſs Buſineſs and Pains, than the Apprentice, (and he perhaps a Gentlemans Son, and with whom the Maſter hath a good ſumm of money) is employed in. The very going to carry out and bring home Wares and Commodities, to receive money and diſpatch other buſineſs, the heaving and lifting of Goods and divers other things, are ſuch as of neceſſity muſt be done, and could not otherwiſe be done at ſo cheap a rate. And if it be well look'd into, I believe there will appear more reaſon for ſome remedy to correct the abuſes of ill Maſters in the miſemployment of their Apprentices in things not anſwering the end of their being put Apprentice, than for any allowance for their Maintenance.</p>
            <p>But it is farther, to be conſidered in this caſe, that the Maſters ordinarily contract two ſeveral Obligations: One with the Parent, Relation, or Friend of the Apprentice, in-conſideration of the Mony by him given; the other, with the Apprentice himſelf by Indenture; and both theſe abſolute, after the Mony paid, and the Indentures executed; and in this caſe both are to be ſatisfied. And certainly, if that to the Apprentice, who committed the firſt fault, then much more that to the Friend, who is without fault. And if that muſt be proportonable to the Obligation, as it ought to be, for <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> are words taken from the <hi>mutual</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions of Material things, and applied to Moral Actions, then can it not be leſs than the whole Money, and the Intereſt, and the Expence the Party is put to for the recovery thereof. Beſides, the Publick is to be conſidered in the caſe; For it is of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to the Publickweal, that Juſtice be duly adminiſtred; but to allow the Maſter any part of this Money, would be to let him take advantage of his own wrong; for his advantage by the diſappointment of his Apprentice, might be much more than all the Money: And beſides, it would be in effect to give Impunity, and thereby great Encouragement to an Abuſe, and to eſtabliſh Iniquity by a Law.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And as unreaſonable as this is, yet ſome have the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to pretend and alledge <hi>The future benefit they might have by their Apprentices,</hi> as <hi>a reaſonable conſideration why they ſhould not make any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51034:7"/>return of the Money.</hi> And it ſeems this is not only the opinion of Trades-men, but alſo of ſome Attorneys or Solicitors, and even of Council too about the City. I have ſeen an Anſwer in <hi>Chancery</hi> upon Oath and with Counſels hands to it (as is uſual) by a Citizen, who received near 100 <hi>l.</hi> with an Apprentice and very obſtinately put him away, wherein is alledged to this purpoſe, That the Apprentice was capable of doing him good Service, and he would not have taken 200 <hi>l.</hi> for his Time and future Service. I have alſo known a Citizen who received no leſs than 400 <hi>l.</hi> with an Apprentice, who as the Citizen himſelf confeſs'd to me, did his Buſineſs exceeding well, but by ill Company, (and ſome of the Citizens own Family) was inveagled to run out a good part of a fair Portion, and after all Accounts cleared, this Man had the Conſcience upon ſuch pretences as theſe, to retain no leſs than 200 <hi>l.</hi> of that money. Which the Young-mans Friends choſe rather to yield to, and accept of what they could get, than to hazard the Expence of much of the reſt in a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Suit under ſuch diſcouragements as theſe I have mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And upon this occaſion I cannot but take notice of <hi>Another unreaſonable Practice,</hi> which the ſame Perſon to excuſe himſelf, pretended to be no more than Uſual. He charges his Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice with the keeping of his Caſh, and yet orders him to leave his Keys when he goes abroad upon his buſineſs; and yet again requires him to make a ſtrict account, and to make up of his own, what is wanting. How ſuch Men can ſatisfie their Conſciences in ſuch things, I cannot underſtand. But this by the by.</p>
            <p>The ſame Opinion I have heard maintain'd by others, who had not any particular concern in any ſuch caſe, but only general, as Citizens and Trades-men. So ſtrangely are many Men in this vitious and corrupt Age, blinded with prejudice, in what is, or may be, their own concern, that one would think they had not only extinguiſh'd all ſenſe of Religion, but moreover put off, not only the Moral, but even Rational part, as to theſe things, of Humanity alſo. Were it not ſo, could ſuch Men have ſuch hard and inhumane hearts, as not to be affected with the Ruine of a Man in their own Family, or to have no Charity or Pity for the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of one committed to their care, or to have no Compaſſion for the trouble and affliction it muſt be to the Relations and Friends, who had dealt with them, and that upon great truſt and confidence; yet it might be expected, that, if not out of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51034:8"/>Generoſity, at leaſt out of regard to their own Credit and Reputation, they ſhould reſtore the whole Money without trouble.</p>
            <p>But inſtead of that, we often find the quite contrary in ſuch Men, who being better able <hi>to tell their ſtory</hi> than the poor young Lad, make it their firſt buſineſs to raiſe as great prejudice againſt him in his Parents and Friends as may be, and having gotten the advantage of an apparent fault, think they muſt needs be believed in whatever other fine <hi>probable ſtories</hi> they can contrive; and with paſſionate or eaſie Men they often do their buſineſs by this means, without more of do. Or if that will not ſo eaſily paſs, they will be ſo very fair, as to offer a <hi>Referrence</hi> to two Citizens, whereof one, who muſt be of their own chooſing, to be ſure ſhall be ſuch as will do nothing but according to his private Inſtructions, or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever according to the falſe Principles before mentioned, and can with more confidence urge thoſe things in another's behalf, than perhaps he could in his own; and the other (if a Man who lives in the Countrey, and hath little to do with Traders, as it often happens, can, among his ſmall aquaintance, meet with one to act for him,) if he be not ſtrongly prepoſſeſſed with theſe falſe principles, yet his own experience can ſatisfie both himſelf and his Friend, that it is much better to yield to unreaſonable terms, than make uſe of a Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe. So beſure the Maſter comes off with good advantage that way, and with Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit too, as he thinks, for being ſo fair as to refer what he had already in his hands. But if he chance to meet with one, who eaſily ſees through theſe little tricks and policies, and will not ſo be put off, then as the temptation becomes double upon him, (for now his Reputation alſo is like to be concern'd,) ſo nothing will be ſtuck at, which may ſerve either to repreſent the Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice as ill as may be, or to cauſe delay, and make the Proceedings tedious and tireſome to one whoſe abode and buſineſs lies perhaps far remote from the City, or in the end to baffle the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The other <hi>Encouragement</hi> which is taken for theſe Abuſes, is from the great <hi>Diſadvantage Men who live remote from the City are under in the proſecution of their Remedy;</hi> for their Expence in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hither, and lying here for that purpoſe, and their Loſs by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of their buſineſs at home, and the Charges of the Suit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their vexation and trouble, is uſually as much or more than they recover. Whereas a Citizen is at home all the while, is but little hindred in his buſineſs, and at no Expence more than for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51034:8"/>the bare proceedings at the Law, unleſs it be ſuch as he will not be willing to own. And this ought alſo to be taken into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in the giving Relief, that ſuch Abuſes may have as little encouragement upon this occaſion as may be.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>the REMEDY</hi> which I conceive is already in the power of our Courts of Juſtice to give, is, that an Action being brought by the Apprentice upon his Indenture, and laid not in <hi>London,</hi> but in <hi>Middleſex,</hi> or ſome other convenient County, if it come to Tryal, that upon motion, a ſpecial Jury (if in <hi>Middleſex</hi>) be granted, of ſuch as are not Traders, or take no Apprentices; or if it come to an Enquiry of damages, that that be done by ſuch a Jury, and before a Judge, in their Sittings upon <hi>Middleſex</hi> cauſes, or in the Circuit.</p>
            <p>And this is a Remedy which hath theſe <hi>Qualifications</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it. 1. It is I conceive, already <hi>in the power of our Judges</hi> to grant it. 2. It is for the <hi>Honour of our Laws,</hi> and a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Inſtance that they are not ſo defective for the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice as many Men imagine. 3. It is a <hi>juſt and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> Remedy, reſtraining the Abuſes of all men, without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any inconvenience upon good and honeſt Men. 4. It is very <hi>neceſſary,</hi> for the Abuſes of this kind, are grown very common and notorious. 5. It is very likely to be <hi>Effectual,</hi> it is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate to take away the very occaſion and encouragements of them. 6. And yet is <hi>no more than neceſſary:</hi> For what Juſtice can be expected from Men generally under ſuch Prejudices, as theſe? And though the Jury be properly Judges of the matter of Fact, yet for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Sheriff,</hi> who returns the Jury, and returns whom he pleaſeth to exerciſe the part of a Judge in ſumming up the Evidence and directing the ſame Jury which he himſelf hath returned, is more than the Judges themſelves do, a thing ſubject to much Corruption and Abuſe, and doth well deſerve to be taken into conſideration for a Remedy. Beſides, there doth many times ariſe matter of Law upon the Evidence, which could not be foreſeen. And the great difference of the Counſel which may be retained on the one ſide and on the other, whereby many times a good Cauſe may be run down, doth often require a more conſiderable Judge than an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Sheriff,</hi> to direct the Jury, and prevent their being miſled.</p>
            <p>It remains now only to give a brief Relation of what hath been done, in order to the putting of this Remedy in practice, and with what Succeſs. And this I had done, and therewith
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51034:9"/>given ſome further proof of ſome of the mattes before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: But upon further conſideration, thought fit to leave it out at preſent, and defer it to another time, intending to do it then more largely if there be occaſion, and if the ſucceſs of this doth not make that labour needleſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript to the Citizens.</head>
            <p>SHould any one upon peruſal of this Paper, ſuppoſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor no Friend to the City, he would be ſo far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſtaken, that from the ſame matter from whence he ſuppoſes that, the contrary may be demonstrated, and that by ſeveral Reaſons. <hi>1.</hi> The wickedneſs of ſuch an Abuſe, conſidered with ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances as uſually accompany it, is plainly of the moſt hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous degree next to Murther, far more heinous than Picking of Pockets, Theft, or Robbery: For though it doth not deſtroy the Perſon immediately, it doth often totally ruine his well-being, and the Families that might have proceeded from him, and not ſeldome occaſions the ruine of his Perſon. And as ſuch Crimes do uſually provoke the Judgments of God upon ſuch particular Perſons as are guilty of them; ſo when they become publick Sins, which may be by commonneſs, Connivance and Impunity, they involve the whole Community in the Guilt, and provoke common Calamities. And it is no ſmall Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to endeavour to remove and avert ſuch Miſchiefs. <hi>2.</hi> The Remedy propoſed is ſo moderate, reaſonable, and favourable, that it hath been thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome very conſiderable Perſons more mild than ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do need and deſerve. And the very endeavour to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> an one, is no ſmall Kindneſs, in regard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at, if it be not neglected, it may prevent others more ſevere. It is therefore to be wiſhed that it may be taken into due conſideration, and that all good Citizens in their ſeveral places uſe all endeavours to correct and extirpate theſe Abuſes, and thereby avert the Judgments of God, or however extricate themſelves out of the common Guilt, and make a more ſevere Remedy needleſs.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
